Guide to the Kathleen Kearney Walsh Papers AIA.029
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kathleen Kearney Walsh Papers
1937-1995
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Walsh, Kathleen Kearney
AIA.029
1.44 Linear Feet in 1 card box, 1 manuscript box, and 1 media box
Kathleen Kearney Walsh, president of the United Irish Counties (UIC) Ladies' Auxiliary and financial secretary to the Offaly Social and Athletic Club, was a prominent member of the greater New York City area Irish American community in the mid- and late-20th century. She served numerous positions in UIC leadership, including the organization's first woman President. This collection contains photographs, correspondence, memoranda, event programs, newspaper clippings, membership cards, video cassettes, and an audio recording documenting Walsh's personal life, role in New York Irish American social circles, efforts to promote Irish cultural traditions, and her unique position as a woman of senior leadership in Irish social organizations in the city.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains photographs, correspondence, memoranda, event programs, newspaper clippings, membership cards, video cassettes, and an audio recording documenting the personal life of Kathleen Kearney Walsh and her involvement in various Irish American organizations, including the United Irish County (UIC) Association Ladies Auxiliary, the Offaly Social and Athletic Club, and the Irish Ladies' Hospital Cheer Committee. The materials illustrate her role in New York Irish American social circles, her efforts to promote Irish cultural traditions, and her unique position as a woman of senior leadership in Irish social organizations in the city.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy be made, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
Archives of Irish America County Societies Collection (AIA 003)
United Irish Counties Association Records (AIA 056)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Kathleen Walsh D'Arcy in 2002. The accession number associated with this gift is 1997.017.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Kathleen Kearney Walsh, president of the United Irish Counties (UIC) Ladies' Auxiliary and financial secretary to the Offaly Social and Athletic Club, was a prominent member of the greater New York City area Irish American community in the mid- and late-20th century. The daughter of Denis Kearney and Teresa Digan Kearney, Kathleen was born in Tullamore, County Offaly. She attended the Convent of Mercy in Tullamore, finished her schooling in Dublin, and then emigrated to the United States in 1925. She married orchestra leader Patrick Walsh in 1937. At the age of 15, she became the first financial secretary of the Offaly Club. She later became the organization's first woman president (the first woman to be elected the president of an Irish county organization), holding the office for eight different terms. She was also the first woman delegate to the UIC; the first woman Vice President of the UIC; first woman Director of the UIC, serving on the Board for 12 years; and President of the UIC Ladies Auxiliary. She also acted as a member of the UIC Feis Committee for over 45 years in an effort to promote Irish cultural activities. She later founded and then acted as the chairperson of the Irish Ladies' Hospital Cheer Committee, fundraising, donating gifts, and spending time with patients, initially focusing on those with tuberculosis and in cancer hospitals, but later with an expanded emphasis.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically.
Offaly (Ireland); Irish Americans -- New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; United Irish Counties Association of N.Y.
- "A Bit of Blarney", undated; 1 reel (Box 4)
- Corrigan, Douglas, 1938, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- County Offaly Membership Book, 1927-1929 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- "A Day in Rockaway with Mr. and Mrs. Tim Curry", 1 reel (Box 4)
- Event Programs, 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Irish Ladies' Hospital Cheer Committee, 1954-1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1947-1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Offaly Social and Athletic Club, 1974-1977 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Photographs, circa 1930-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- United Irish Counties Association: Ladies Auxiliary, 1944, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Videocassette #1: United Irish Counties Association Feis dances and speeches; Kilkenny Association dinner dance; Rev. Timothy J. Shanley Funeral Mass; Masquerade Ball, 1953; 1 videodisc (dvd) 1 videocassette (Box 4, Box 1, Cd 1, Box 2, 8mm film reel TAM/WAG AIA-29-a)
- Videocassette #2: St. Patrick's Day Parade; Offaly Ball, Mar 17, 1954; 1 videodisc (dvd) 1 videocassette (Box 4, Box 1, Cd 1, Box 2, 8mm film reel TAM/WAG AIA-29-b)
- Videocassette #3: "Let's Sing", 1947; 1 videodisc (dvd) 1 videocassette (Box 1, Cd 1, Box 4)